Guide to the John A. Blume Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
John A. Blume papers
1903-1994
1928-1994
SC0684
Blume, John A., 1909-
49.5 Linear feet
Collection includes subject and reference files on earthquakes and earthquake-resistant design; slides, photographs, and videos pertaining to earthquakes and earthquake engineering; course files as both student and teacher; reports and other materials on Diablo Canyon Nuclear Plant; and talks, lectures, and reprints by Blume. Some materials pertain to the career of his father, Charles A. Blume. Items of note include US Coast and Geodetic Survey reports on California cities, 1930s-40s; photo album published by Kinnear Manufacturing on fire retardants in the San Francisco fire of 1906; and an album of views of San Francisco, 1915.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
Collection is unprocessed and in remote storage. For access, please contact the University Archivist.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Blume, known as the father of earthquake engineering, earned his B.S. in civil engineering in 1933 and his engineer's degree in 1935 at Stanford University. He was a construction engineer on the San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge and later worked for Standard Oil. In 1945 he established his own structural and earthquake engineering firm. He returned to Stanford in 1964 for graduate work and earned his doctorate in civil engineering in 1967. He died in 2002.
Description of the Collection
Collection includes subject and reference files on earthquakes and earthquake-resistant design; slides, photographs, and videos pertaining to earthquakes and earthquake engineering; course files as both student and teacher; reports and other materials on Diablo Canyon Nuclear Plant; and talks, lectures, and reprints by Blume. Some materials pertain to the career of his father, Charles A. Blume. Items of note include US Coast and Geodetic Survey reports on California cities, 1930s-40s; photo album published by Kinnear Manufacturing on fire retardants in the San Francisco fire of 1906; and an album of views of San Francisco, 1915.
Access Terms
Blume, Charles A.; Blume, John A., 1909-; Stanford University. School of Engineering.; U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey; Civil engineers.; Diablo Canyon Nuclear Powerplant (Calif.); Earthquake engineering.; Earthquake resistant design.; San Francisco Earthquake and Fire, Calif., 1906
Collection Contents
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2003-281
  - Notes, testimonies, file reports, etc. for hearings regarding earthquakes, 1978-1981 (many files re Diablo Canyon Nuclear Plant) (Box 1)
  - Product files, research models, instruments and equipment, 1958-1977 (Box 2)
  - Reprints by other writers (Box 2)
  - Files re Peru earthquake of January 1958 (Box 2)
  - “Jokes and talk material” (Box 2)
  - Bibliographic references (Box 3)
  - NVO project materials [box as a whole covers 1966-1988] (Box 3)
  - Soil data Jan. 1966 by Blume (Box 3)
  - SLAC 1964 info (EQ studies/survey) (Box 3)
  - SU 20th class reunion (class of ‘32 or ’33) (Box 3)
  - Earthquake Engineering and Stanford, 1964 report (Box 3)
  - Stanford course files (as student and as professor) (Box 3)
  - Blume’s evaluations of papers by other professionals (Box 3)
  - Reports by Blume & Associates 1978, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Subject files on:
    - Shock impact, table pulses & blasts (Box 3)
    - Sound acoustics and music (Box 3)
    - Tests and devices (Box 3)
    - Random excitation (Box 3)
    - Design for blast & blast shelters (Box 3)
    - Future seismic research work (Box 3)
    - Human perception of motion (Box 3)
  - Subject files on:
    - vibration (Box 4)
    - EQ records, damage (Box 4)
    - EQ-resistant design (Box 4)
  - Files on various structural entities (grandstands, stadiums, etc) (Box 4)
  - Files on law (Box 4)
  - Files on materials (Box 4)
  - Subject files on:
    - EQ-resistant design (Box 5)
    - Code work on EQ (Box 5)
    - Seismology instruments (Box 5)
  - Diablo Canyon Nuclear Plant files (Box 5)
  - SRP files [unsure of meaning – structural something?] (Box 5)
  - Papers by other professionals (Box 5)
  - US Coast and Geodetic Survey reports re California cities 1930s-40s (Box 5)
  - More subject files (Box 6)
  - More US Coast and Geodetic Survey reports (Box 6)
  - Papers by Blume (Box 6)
  - Architectural exam 1949 [licensing-type exam] (Box 6)
  - Lehigh trip 1972 (Box 6)
  - Tall buildings committee files (Box 6)
  - EERI minutes, Board of Directors 1978-79 (Box 6)
  - Clippings on various earthquakes (Box 6)
  - Coast Geodetic and EERI assorted materials 1949-50 (Box 6)
  - Blume’s papers and reprints (Box 7)
  - Assorted Diablo Canyon Nuclear Plant materials (Box 7)
  - Assorted Diablo Canyon Nuclear Plant materials (Box 8)
  - Nuclear Regulatory Commission legal suit (S. Carolina) – transcript of Blume’s deposition (Box 8)
  - Tentative Provisions for Development of Seismic Regulations, 1978 report (Box 8)
  - Long Beach condominium complex files (structural issues) (Box 9)
  - EQ damage evaluation data for California (Box 9)
  - Assorted Diablo Canyon Nuclear Plant files, late 1960s-1970s (Box 9)
  - Data re Blume, Hosgri, Spectra (Box 9)
  - Meeting and data files, 1976 (Box 9)
  - Diablo Canyon material 1977-78:
    - Study of Trifunac Attenuation (Box 10)
    - PGE Diffuse Area Probabilistic Study 1977 (Box 10)
    - Santa Barbara earthquake Aug. 13, 1978 (Box 10)
  - Data re Alexander building, San Francisco, 1956 (Box 10)
  - Diablo Canyon:
    - Clippings (Box 10)
    - Letter from attorneys 1986 (Box 10)
    - More legal and engineering documents 1983 (Box 10)
  - Diablo Canyon:
    - Auxiliary building analysis (Box 11)
    - Annulus spectra 1977-83 (Box 11)
    - Internal report – URS/Blume on DC 1982 (Box 11)
  - Materials related to work for PG&E (Box 11)
  - Cornell correspondence – review of Blume document 1976 (Box 11)
  - PG&E proposals 1978 (Box 11)
  - Bechtel (Box 11)
  - PG&E 1982 (Box 11)
  - Press re: “DC flap” (Box 11)
  - Talks and lectures by Blume: Stanford, 1939-69; other 1946-69 (Box 12)
  - Talks and reprints 1957-59 (Box 13)
  - Blume’s student notes at SU, 1928-32 (Box 13)
  - Cost data for buildings (Box 13)
  - Testimony in cases (Box 13)
  - Talk (?) on Relationship of Peak Ground Acceleration, Intensity and Local Magnitude, 1981 (Box 13)
  - Testimony South Carolina Electric & Gas, 1981 (Box 13)
  - EQ Evaluation Data for California – draft 1984 (Box 13)
  - EQ Evaluation Data for California – draft 1985 (Box 13)
  - Applied Technology Council Project/Meetings 1984 (Box 14)
  - Fees & Services – collected documentation (Box 14)
  - JAB-QS -, Long Beach material 1978-82 (Box 14)
  - Paper redone by Blume, etc, 1988 (Edward C. Robinson 1950) (Box 14)
  - Alexander building files – 1962 note by JAB (Box 14)
  - JAB publicity clippings, souvenirs & scrapbook data “Box #2,3” (Box 15)
  - Notebook for CE105 Problems, 1932 (Box 15)
  - Steel Moment Frame Connection (publication) (Box 15)
  - Diablo Canyon Nuclear Power Plant – notebook 1977 (Box 16)
  - Advances in Earthquake Engineering 1980 (Continuing Studies notebook) (Box 16)
  - Computer programs written & used at SU (1965) (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous publications/reprints (Box 16)
  - Atomic Energy – South Carolina material (Box 17)
  - Wind Loading – information (Box 17)
  - Blume – “Professional Qualifications” (Box 17)
  - CA – Board of Registration – structural exams (Box 17)
  - Colliers – 1956 – (1906 earthquake) (Box 17)
  - Newspaper – SF Chron 1956 (Box 17)
  - CA – Board of Registration – civil eng. exams (Box 17)
  - SU 1933 Class – 1953 reunion (Box 17)
  - CA Division of Highways – Civil Service exams 1933 (Box 17)
  - Papers, 1977-82 (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous publications (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous unsorted materials – ephemera/publications (Box 18)
  - Binders of photographs of earthquakes (Box 19)
  - Binders of photographs of earthquakes (Box 20)
  - Notebooks of Blume (Box 20)
  - Loose pages from photo book (Box 20)
  - Slides and photographs (mostly professional, some personal) (Box 21)
  - Slides and slide transparencies (Box 22)
  - Slides (Box 23)
  - Memorabilia related to trip (China?) (Box 23)
  - Photographs (Box 23)
  - Diablo Canyon Reports – prepared for PGE 1968-87 (Box 24)
  - Other documentation related to Diablo Canyon 1970s (Reanalysis Criteria & Reports) (Box 24)
  - Professional Organization directories (Box 24)
  - Professional Organization documents (Box 24)
  - Business related – miscellaneous (Box 24)
  - File labeled Stanford (Box 24)
  - File labeled Misc (Box 24)
  - File labeled SF 1906 data (Box 24)
  - File labeled Codes, etc. (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous materials (Box 25)
  - USCGS (?) (Box 25)
  - EERI (Box 25)
  - Miscellany including some loose photos (Box 25)
  - Excerpts from Nils Blume autobiography (relates to 1906 quake) (Box 25)
  - Genealogy – Blume (Box 25)
  - Photos (Box 25)
  - Charles A. Blume – file (Box 25)
  - JAB personal data – genealogy, etc. (Box 25)
  - CAB job photos (Box 25)
  - Clippings (Box 25)
  - JAB job record with Brunnier (Box 25)
  - Various small publications – by Blume and others (Box 25)
  - Earthquake Evaluation data report – part 1 – 1985 draft (Box 25)
  - Clippings & other unsorted material (Box 25)
  - Folder: April 18, 1906 – S. F. earthquake (Box 26)
  - Publications: mostly by Blume (Box 26)
  - Box with material related to 1980 trip to China, Japan, etc. (Box 26)
  - 1941 datebook (Box 26)
  - Slide catalogue – notebook (Box 26)
  - Fire Retardants in San Francisco Fire 1906 – photo album published by Kinnear Manufacturing (Box 26)
  - 2 photo albums (Box 26)
  - 1915 – Album of views of SF (Box 26)
  - Personal material from Claire Webster (Box 26)
  - Official guide to Pan Pacific 1915 Expo (Box 26)
  - Publications:
    - Yanev “Technical Communication: The Lice, Turkey Earthquake of September 6, 1975” Nov. 1975 (Box 27)
    - Summary of Structural Dynamics Research at Stanford 1946-53 – August 1953 (Box 27)
    - San Francisco Seismic Safety Investigation, June 1974 (Box 27)
    - Program and Abstracts of Papers. National Conference on Earthquake Engineering. Investigations of the San Fernando Earthquake – Feb. 1972 (Box 27)
    - A Low Cost Method to Rehabilitate Unsafe Schools in Earthquake-Prone Areas (Box 27)
    - Effects of Earthquake on Engineering Structures (notes), 1929 (Box 27)
    - Sozen, Rosset. “Structural Damage Caused by the 1976 Guatemala Earthquake” March 1976 (Box 27)
    - Research Agenda: The 19 September 1985 Mexico Earthquake. January 1986 (Box 27)
    - Damage Evaluation for Imperial County Services Building, El Centro, California. February 1980 (Box 27)
    - A Comparative Study of Pulse and Step-Type Loads on a Simple Vibratory System. Jan. 1952 (Box 27)
    - Development of a ‘Deformation Model’ of a building for the Study of Blast Load Effects. June 1952 (Box 27)
    - Jacobsen, “On a General Method of Solving Second Order Differential Equations by Phase-Plane-Displacements.” Report no. 13 (Box 27)
    - Architect & Engineer, Sept. 1958 (Box 27)
    - Bulletin of the Seismological Society of America, April 1972 (Box 27)
    - EERI Delegation to the People’s Republic of China Jan. 1982 (Box 27)
    - EERI Reconnaissance Report Miyagi-Ken-Oki, Japan Earthquake of June 12, 1978. December 1978 (Box 27)
    - EERI Newsletters May 1979, July 1981 (Box 27)
    - Neville Donovan, ”Notes for EERI Course on Seismic Risk Analysis” Feb. 9, 1978 (Box 27)
    - Earthquake Data compiled by H. M. Engle Aug. 1932 [copies of assorted documents] (Box 27)
    - ASCE Technical Seminar – resources 1960s (Box 27)
    - Design Seminar, Structural Engineering Conference of ASCI May 1967 (Box 27)
    - EERI 1968 State-of-the-Art Symposium EQ Engineering of buildings, Feb. 1968 (Box 27)
    - Various resources marked “File #9.3” (Box 27)
    - Military Engineer, Jan-Feb. 1973 (Box 27)
    - Peter Yanev, Field Notes Miyagi-Ken-Oki, Japan Earthquake of June 12, 1978 (Box 27)
    - URS/Blume & Associates, Review of Seismic Studies of Proposed Nuclear Waste Repository [Nevada], June 1983 (Box 27)
    - Tom Andres, “A Brief Account of Responses to the Santa Barbara EQ, August 13, 1978” (Box 27)
    - 1948 building codes for San Francisco (Box 27)
    - Assorted steel company catalogs 1903-1928 (Box 27)
  - Slides, including glass lantern slides (Box 28)
  - Framed photos, certificate, plaques, awards (Box 29)
  - Plaques, certificates awards (Box 30)
  - Large mounted photos – early 20th century (Box 30)
  - Post ’06 photos (Box 30)
  - Some family photos (Box 30)
  - Family Stereographs (Box 30)
  - Slides and a few photos of EQ damage 1973 and other dates (Box 31)
  - Maps, a few reports, and many photos re California EQs – 1952 and other dates (Box 31)
  - Videos [VHS unless otherwise noted] (Box 32)
  - ITS / Mode control method (Box 32)
  - Construction Automation & Robots – Boyd Paulson 1990 (Box 32)
  - FEMA workshop – Safety of Dams 1986 (2 copies) (Box 32)
  - Computer Simulation of the Painter Street & Dumbarton Bridges (Box 32)
  - California OES –“An Ounce of Prevention…” (2 copies) (Box 32)
  - Costa Rica Earthquake (Box 32)
  - Miyagi-Ken-Oki, Japan earthquake (Box 32)
  - JDO Earthquake Presentation 1991 (Box 32)
  - Quake Defense (Box 32)
  - Earthquake – Haresh Shah 1994 (Box 32)
  - Earthquakes Channel 7 1994 (Box 32)
  - National Bureau of Standards – Mexico Earthquake 1985 (2 copies) (Box 32)
  - Philippine Earthquake NHK Special 1990 (2 copies) (Box 32)
  - Middle Japan Sea earthquake (Box 32)
  - Major Earthquakes (Box 32)
  - Earthquake (Box 32)
  - Tacoma Narrows [3/4 inch tape] (Box 32)
  - Unmarked ¾ inch tape (Box 32)
  - Headline Earthquakes 1980 (Box 32)
  - Glass Slides (Box 33)
  - Regular slides (Box 33)
  - 1 film – Interferometry in Earthquake Research (Box 33)
  - 1 unmarked microfilm roll (Box 33)
  - 1 film – Milestones of the Century (Box 33)
  - 1 record (45 rpm?) – Sounds of earthquakes (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous publs (Box 33)